Register of the Wallace E. Adams Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Wallace E. Adams papers,
1900-1978
79013
Adams, Wallace E. (Wallace Earl), 1926-
20 manuscript boxes, 2 card file boxes, 1 oversize box (9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Notes, drafts, photocopies of French governmental documents, computer data cards, press summaries, and printed matter, relating to French politics and foreign policy during the Third and Fourth Republics, and especially to the career of the French politician André Tardieu. Mostly research material for the doctoral dissertation by W. E. Adams, "André Tardieu and French Foreign Policy, 1902-1919" (Stanford University, 1959). Includes some original notes by Tardieu.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
1926 Born, Silverton, Oregon
1949 Bachelor of Science degree, University of Oregon
1951-1954 Special assistant to the Executive Officer, United States of America Operations Mission to France
1958-1962 Assistant professor of European history, Arizona State University
1959 PhD, Stanford University
1962 Visiting professor, University of California, Santa Barbara
1963-1970s Professor, Arizona State University
Scope and Content Note
The Wallace E. Adams papers in the Hoover Institution Archives consist primarily of Adams's writings and the research materials he accumulated over an academic career devoted to 20th century French history and, in particular, the career of the French politician André Tardieu. There is also a considerable amount of materials relating to Adams's service in France as an aid official with the United States of America Operations Mission to France, a successor to activities of the Marshall Plan.
Adams completed his doctoral dissertation on Tardieu at Stanford University, and continued to conduct research on Tardieu's role in French politics, especially in relation to French colonial policies in Africa, thereafter. He collected a number of primary sources, including some of Tardieu's notebooks and unpublished writings, which form a separate series within the collection (see ANDRÉ TARDIEU FILE). There is a good deal of material in the collection relating to the so-called N'Goko Sangha affair in French West Africa and its possible impact on the origins of World War I, including copies of company records and official correspondence (see RESEARCH MATERIALS).
As a graduate student, Adams had become interested in the possibilities afforded by computers to quantify trends in modern French politics. RESEARCH MATERIALS contains Adams's work in this regard, including statistical analyses of parliamentary voting records and government instability during the French Third Republic.
The series concerning Adams's service in France during the 1950s contains press summaries and other materials that provide information on American perceptions of French politics and economic life during a period of Cold War tensions (see UNITED STATES OF AMERICA OPERATIONS MISSION TO FRANCE FILE).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Tardieu, André, 1876-1945.; World War, 1914-1918--France.; France--Politics and government--20th century.; France--Foreign relations--20th century.
Collection Contents
- Biographical File, 1965-1966. (Box 1)
  Curricula vitae and grant proposal
  - Curricula vitae and grant proposal (Folder 1: 1)
- Correspondence, 1954-1978 (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - Unidentified, 1978 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Grazia, Alfred de, 1957 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Harrold, James E., Jr., 1954 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Jabr, Barbara J., 1954 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Rassekh, N., 1954 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Washington, P. W., 1954 (Folder 1: 7)
- Writings, 1955-1968., See also Research Materials below (Box 1-3)
  Article, chronology, dissertation, notes, outlines, and paper, arranged chronologically.
  - "The Government of France in 1929," n.d. (Folder 1: 8)
    Typescript
  - Paper on the Croix de Feu, n.d. (Folder 1: 9)
    Notes, bibliography, and typescript
  - "The Political and Social Structure of the French Chamber of Deputies, 1924-1928," 1955
    - Chronology. (Folder 1: 10)
    - Draft. (Folder 1: 11)
      Typescript with holograph notes
    - Final paper. (Folder 1: 12-13)
      Typescripts
  - "André Tardieu and French Foreign Policy, 1902-1919," doctoral dissertation, Stanford University, 1955
    - Abstract. (Folder 1: 14)
    - Outline. (Folder 1: 15)
    - Chronology. (Folder 1: 16)
    - Preliminary bibliography. (Folder 1: 17-19)
    - Drafts. (Box-folder 2: 1-5)
      Typescripts with holograph notes
    - Drafts. (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
    - Thesis (incomplete). (Folder 3: 3)
    - Correspondence, n.d. (Folder 3: 4)
  - "The N'Goko Sangha Affair," c. 1962
    - Chronology and outline. (Folder 3: 5)
    - Comments. (Folder 3: 6)
      Holograph
  - "Cabinet Instability in the French Third Republic," 1963
    - Notes. (Folder 3: 7)
      Holograph and typescript
    - Draft proposal. (Folder 3: 8)
    - Correspondence, 1963 (Folder 3: 9)
  - "Europe since World War II," c. 1968. (Folder 3: 10)
    Outline of proposed anthology. Typescript
- André Tardieu File, 1916-1957. (Box 3-4)
  Biographical file, correspondence, voting record, and writings, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Biographical file, 1945-1957. (Folder 3: 11)
    Printed copies of memorial pamphlets, and typescript of speech by Michel Missoffe at dedication of plaque commemorating Tardieu, Paris, France, 1953 July 6
  - Correspondence, 1927. (Folder 3: 12)
    Copies of letters sent by Tardieu to Michel Missoffe
  - Voting record, 1928. (Folder 3: 13)
    Booklet recording Tardieu's votes in the French Chamber of Deputies
  - Writings, 1916-1940
    - Notebooks
      - General, n.d. (Folder 3: 14-15)
      - "Comité secret," 1916.
        Tardieu's transcription of secret sessions of the French parliament
        - Original. (Folder 3: 16)
        - Translation by Wallace E. Adams. (Folder 3: 17)
      - Outline for book on history of Western Europe, c. 1930s
        - "L'essor de l'Europe" (Folder 4: 1)
        - "La fin du Moyen-Age" (Folder 4: 2)
    - "La révolution à refaire," c. 1940.
      Unpublished manuscript transcribed by Wallace E. Adams
      - Volume one (fragment). (Folder 4: 3)
        Typescript, with English translation by Adams
      - Volume three. (Folder 4: 4)
        Typescript, in French only
- United States of America Operations Mission to France File, 1948-1954. (Box 4-6)
  Articles and clippings, briefing book, briefing papers, correspondence, filing manual, personnel list, press summaries, printed matter, reports, and speeches, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Articles and clippings, 1950-1953 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Briefing book, 1952 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Briefing papers, 1949-1953 (Folder 4: 7)
  - Correspondence
    - 1949-1952 (Folder 5: 1)
    - 1953-1954 (Folder 5: 2)
  - Filing manual, n.d. (Folder 5: 3)
  - Personnel list, 1953 (Folder 5: 4)
  - Press summaries
    - 1951-1953 (Folder 5: 5)
    - 1954
      - January-February (Folder 5: 6)
      - March-April (Folder 5: 7)
      - May-June (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Printed matter
    - 1951 (Folder 6: 2)
    - 1952-1953 (Folder 6: 3)
  - Reports
    - 1948-1951 (Folder 6: 4)
    - 1952 (Folder 6: 5-6)
    - 1953-1954 (Folder 6: 7)
  - Speeches, 1950-1952 (Folder 6: 8)
- Research Materials, 1900-1977. (Box 7-18)
  Album, articles, bibliographies, biographical data sheets, clippings, code sheets, company records, computer codes, correspondence, indexes, interviews, maps, monograph excerpts, monographs, official correspondence, notebooks, notes, parliamentary records, serial issues, voting statistics, and work sheets, arranged chronologically by date research undertaken or published, and by physical form therein
  - "The Political and Social Structure of the French Chamber of Deputies, 1924-1928," published 1955
    - Computer codes, n.d. (Folder 7: 1)
    - Maps, n.d. (Folder 7: 2)
    - Notes, n.d. (Folder 7: 3-4)
    - Parliamentary records, 1927 (Folder 7: 5)
    - Voting statistics
      - 1919 (Folder 7: 6)
      - 1928 (Folder 7: 7)
    - Work sheets, n.d. (Folder 7: 8-9)
    - Work sheets, n.d. (Folder 8: 1-5)
    - Work sheets, n.d. (Folder 9: 1-5)
  - "André Tardieu and French Foreign Policy, 1902-1919," submitted 1959 (Box 10)
    - Album
      - Clippings, correspondence, and notes relating to André Tardieu, 1917-1956. (Folder 10: 1)
        Includes copies of letters written by Tardieu to Michel Missoffe, and Wallace E. Adams's correspondence with Jacques Debu-Bridel, Pierre Mille, Michel Missoffe, René Picard, François Piétri, and Pierre Poujet
      - Clippings, correspondence, interviews, and notes relating to André Tardieu, 1945-1954. (Folder 10: 2)
        Includes correspondence between Wallace E. Adams and Henri Cangardel, Maurice Gamelin, H. Stuart Hughes, Gabriel Puaux, Jacques Rey, Max Terrier, and Gordon Wright. Also includes some correspondence neither to nor from Wallace E. Adams
    - Article, 1912 (Folder 10: 3)
    - Clippings, 1910-1954 (Folder 10: 4)
    - Monograph, c. 1910 (Folder 10: 5)
    - Monograph excerpts, 1912 (Folder 10: 6)
    - Notes, n.d. (Folder 10: 7)
    - Work sheets, n.d. (Folder 10: 8)
  - The N'Goko Sangha affair and French colonialism, undertaken 1962-1970s
    - Articles, 1963-1969 (Folder 11: 1)
    - Bibliographies, n.d. (Folder 11: 2-5)
    - Clippings, 1907 (Folder 11: 6)
    - Compagnie N'Goko-Sangha records
      - 1905-1910 (Folder 11: 7)
      - 1922 (Folder 11: 8)
    - Indexes of names, n.d. (Folder 11: 9-10)
    - Maps, n.d. (Folder 11: 11)
    - Monograph excerpts
      - 1900-1910 (Folder 12: 1)
      - 1912-1928 (Folder 12: 2)
      - 1955-1960 (Folder 12: 3)
      - 1969-1977 (Folder 12: 4)
      - 1912 (Folder 12: 5-6)
      - 1934 (Box-folder 13: 1)
      - 1972 (Folder 13: 2)
    - Notebooks, n.d. (Folder 13: 3-4)
    - Notes, n.d. (Folder 13: 5)
    - Official correspondence, largely between the French Foreign Ministry and the Compagnie N'Boko Sangha
      - 1905-1906 (Folder 13: 6)
      - 1907 (Folder 13: 7)
      - 1908 (Box-folder 14: 1)
      - 1909 (Folder 14: 2-4)
      - 1910-1918 (Folder 14: 5)
    - Parliamentary records, 1910 (Folder 14: 6)
  - "Cabinet Instability in the French Third Republic," undertaken 1963-1970s
    - Article, 1960 (Folder 15: 1)
    - Biographical data sheets, n.d.
      - A-C (Folder 15: 2-3)
      - D-K (Folder 15: 4)
      - M-Z (Folder 15: 5)
    - Clipping, 1937 (Box-folder 16: 1)
    - Code sheets, n.d. (Folder 16: 2-5)
    - Monograph excerpts, 1951-1958 (Box-folder 17: 1)
    - Monographs, 1924-1939 (Folder 17: 2-4)
    - Notes, n.d. (Folder 17: 5)
    - Parliamentary records
      - 1910-1911 (Folder 17: 6)
      - 1919-1922 (Box-folder 18: 1)
      - 1924-1927 (Folder 18: 2)
    - Serial issues
      - 1927-1928 (Folder 18: 3)
      - 1928 (Folder 18: 4)
    - Work sheets, n.d. (Folder 18: 5)
- Card File, n.d. (Box 19-20)
  Note cards relating to Wallace E. Adams's research on French historical subjects, especially concerning André Tardieu
- Microfilm, n.d. (Folder 21: 1)
  Ninety-three short strips of microfilmed documents relating to the Versailles Peace Conference of 1919
- Photographs, n.d. (Folder 21: 2)
  One negative and five prints depicting André Tardieu; four prints depicting the residence of André Tardieu; three prints depicting Michel Missoffe(?)
- Printed Matter, 1930-1978. (Box 21-22)
  Monographs and serial issues, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Monographs
    - Michel Missoffe, La vie volontaire d'André Tardieu, 1930 (Folder 21: 3)
    - Fortran: General Information Manual, 1961 (Folder 21: 4)
  - Serial issues
    - French Colonial Studies, no. 2, 1978 (Folder 21: 5)
    - Journal officiel de la République française
      - 1953 December 11-13 (Folder 22: 1)
      - 1954
        - March
          - 10-19 (Folder 22: 2)
          - 20-26 (Folder 22: 3)
          - 27-31 (Folder 22: 4)
        - April 1-9 (Folder 22: 5)
- Oversize Materials, 1927-1935. (Box 23)
  Serial publication, arranged chronologically
  - Le républicain de Belfort
    - 1927 July 6 (Folder 23: 1)
    - 1928
      - March 21 (Folder 23: 2)
      - April
        - 12 (Folder 23: 3)
        - 15 (Folder 23: 4)
      - November 14 (Folder 23: 5)
      - December 5 (Folder 23: 6)
    - 1929
      - December
        - 21 (Folder 23: 7)
        - 28 (Folder 23: 8)
    - 1935 June 26 (Folder 23: 9)